I am both a prince
나는 황자이기도 하지만
And a subject
동시에 신하이기도 하다
How could there be
어찌 조정의 명을 안 따를 수가 있겠나
This is my military seal
이건 내 호부군인일세
I give it to General Chen
진 장군에게 맡기겠네
I hope General Chen
부디 진 장군
Will fulfill his duties diligently
직무에 성심을 다해
Do not disappoint the soldiers
병사들의 기대를 저버리지 말거라
Please rest assured, Your Highness
전하, 걱정하지 마십시오
I
반드시 전하의 기대에 보답하겠습니다
He's so obedient
저렇게 순순히
Just handed over military command like that
두말없이 병권을 내놓다니
In my heart
영 마음이
I'm uneasy
놓이지 않소
A dog that bites
원래 무는 개는
Never barks
짖지 않는 법입니다
In the past
예전에 진왕이 옥에 갇혔을 때
I advised Your Highness
제가 전하께
To go all the way
차라리 끝을 보자고 권했지만
But Your Highness then
그때 전하께서는 망설이셨지요
Chancellor Chen
진 승상
Don't tease me
지금 나한테 뭐라 하시는 거요?
Give the order
명령을 내리시오
Immediately order Qingzhou Army to break camp
즉시 경주군에게 철영을 명하고
Move toward the capital
황성으로 오라고 하거라
Also
그리고
Send Chen Ying
진응에게 밀서를 한 통 더 보내라
Yes
네
This is just my personal letter
이건 내 집안 편지일 뿐인데
Why was it opened?
어찌 뜯긴 흔적이 있는 것이냐?
General Chen Ying ordered
진응 장군께서
All correspondence in the army
오고 가는 서찰은 모두
Must first be sent to him for review
장군에게 먼저 보이라 했습니다
Chen Ying
진응?
Think clearly
잘 생각해야 한다
Whose orders do you follow?
넌 대체 누구 명을 따르는 거냐?
I only follow military orders
오직 군령만을 따를 뿐입니다
Who promoted you all this way?
누가 널 발탁했지는 모르는 거냐?
I really misjudged you
내가 사람을 정말 잘못 봤구나
Get out
나가거라!
Your Highness
전하
Let's have a good drink tonight
저녁에 거하게 마셔보자
Sir
대인
The volunteer army families
의군의 가족들은
All depend on Yiyang's compensation to survive
모두 익양의 부조금에 기대 살고 있습니다
Really can't delay any longer
더 이상 미루면 안 됩니다
Want to talk? Fine
상담이라 좋지
After you're cleaned up
이따가 찾아오너라
The heir
세자와 왕비가
Are both in the capital
도성에 있어
I must consider them
그들의 안위를 생각하지 않을 수 없어
Right now, no matter what
어쨌든 지금은
Cannot act rashly
함부로 움직여서는 안 돼
Who?
누구냐?
Your Highness
전하, 접니다
Zhu Yuanzhi
주원지
What are you doing?
무슨 짓을 하는 것이냐?
At this time
이런 때에
You kill Chen Ying's men
진응의 부하를 죽이다니
Isn't that making things worse?
일을 더 크게 만들 작정이냐?
Your Highness
전하
Look who's here
누가 왔는지 보세요
This old minister
노신이 드디어 전하를 뵙네요
Please rise quickly
어서 일어나세요
Huiji is a thousand li
회길에서 익양까진 천 리나 떨어져 있는데
How did you come?
어찌 오셨어요?
Since Your Highness's victory
전하께서 승전하신 이후로
The situation has been crystal clear
형세는 이미 불 보듯 뻔했습니다
So I
그래서
Left Huiji Commandery early
일찌감치 회길군에서 빠져나와
Secretly returned to the capital to plan
비밀리에 도성에 돌아가 준비했습니다
Your Highness
전하
This is what I intercepted from the capital
이건 신이 도성에서 가로챈
A secret letter from Chen Dao to Chen Ying
진도가 진응에게 보낸 밀서입니다
This is critical
사안이 중대하니
Quickly summon Xie Xuan
어서 사현과
And Uncle Qiu together
구승을 함께 불러와라
Zhu Yuanzhi, how dare you
주원지, 네놈이 미쳤구나!
My sister and the heir are still in the capital
누이와 세자가 아직 도성에 있는데
Are you trying to harm them?
해치기라도 하겠다는 거냐?
Brother-in-law
매형
Don't be impulsive
냉정하셔야 합니다
Father
아버지
Say something
말씀 좀 해보세요
Your Highness
전하
Though somewhat offensive
무례를 무릅쓰고
I must speak some words
이 말만은 반드시 해야겠습니다
If Your Highness hesitates further
전하께서 이대로 주저하신다면
Then we'll be like fish on a chopping block
놈들에게 칼자루를 쥐여주고
At others' mercy
저희는 손도 못 쓰고 죽을 뿐입니다
Enough, Zhu Yuanzhi
그만해, 주원지!
Do you know what you're saying?
네놈이 지금 무슨 소리를 하는지 아느냐?
I know Your Highness's concerns
전하께서 뭘 우려하시는지 압니다
But if Your Highness truly dies here
허나 전하께서 여기서 죽기라도 하신다면
Then the princess consort
왕비와
And the heir
세자도
Can they have a good outcome?
과연 무사할 수 있겠습니까?
Your Highness
전하
Strike first to gain advantage
먼저 선수를 치셔야 합니다!